so today we are talking about low do now
treone or LDN for
short now if you don't know what n trone
is it is a drug that was historically
used to treat opioid abstinence and it's
also been used to treat alcohol
abstinence and in some cases you can
actually use it um in weight loss but
today we're talking about it in the
context of the HRT and Integrative
Medicine World well you may be wondering
why would we even have a place or why
would it have a place in the HRT World
well biggest reason that we use it the
biggest indication would be in Hashimoto
disease which is one of the most common
causes of thyroid disease especially in
the developed world and if you think
about it the vast majority of cases of
thyroid disease um hypothyroidism
particularly is caused by Hashimoto so
if you know somebody that has Hashimoto
chances are better check the siblings
better check the parents better check
the kids because they probably have't
anyway so now Trex Zone it is what's
considered a pure opioid antagonist
meaning it purely binds and blocks the
receptor notada it sits on the place
occupies that receptor cool now what
utility does it have in the HRT World
well now TX Zone what happens is it'll
upregulate the this it'll upregulate
what's called opioid growth factor or
ogf for sure now how's it do it let's
talk about it so when you introduce now
Trex Zone what it does is it binds these
ogf receptors well if it binds The
receptors it displaces ogf that was
previously on those receptors guess what
those newly displaced um ogf they need a
new home Your Body compensates by
upregulating more receptors and then
they can bind that so it creates this
bind displace upregulate bind displace
of regulate bind this cyclical uh wash
and repeat rinse and repeat cycle and
what that does is it creates more o ogf
it U regulates more ogf activity and ogf
is a very very very potent
immunomodulator on top of that the these
cycles of find dis Place repeat find
this place repeat also upregulates
what's known as by endorphins and that
also acts like an analgesic um it also
helps immunomodulate as well so through
the the process of increasing more ogf
more B endorphins you're really going to
stimulate the immune system to be more
active and provide more robust response
now when implementing none into
integrative practice or integr program
we want to use the small compounded
doses now the Branded drugs would be
like revia would be a brand version of
it and Vivid draw would be the
injectable version for opioid opioid
abstinence but what we use are the
compound versions we use the compounds
and they're usually somewhere in the
ballpark of half a milligram to four to
5 milligrams and they come in little
compound capsules now the reason why we
want to use small doses not brand doses
such as like 50 milligrams is because
again if this is about the bind displace
ulate bind displace up regulate if you
use those higher doses what happens is
you oversaturate you hit the receptors
you saturate them and then you don't get
that displacement bind up regulate you
don't get that whole cycle so we want to
use the smaller doses so that we don't
oversaturate The receptors because with
each of those bind displac Cycles that's
when you're really going to get more of
imun modular response when introducing
LDN into someone's uh medication
protocol we typically advise they start
taking it somewhere in the evening late
evening and this is really going to
augment that the body's uh Beta dorphin
release response is what it's going to
do so you get a better response in that
terms when you it later in the evening
now the most common side effect people
typically complain about is insomnia and
I always reassure patients that you know
it may suck for the first week or two
but just try to write it out if you can
or just try to take it a little bit
earlier in the day but it usually self
it's usually self-resolving within a few
weeks in terms of titration you
typically want to start off half a
milligram 1 milligram and then as you
tolerate better every few weeks you can
titrate up by about a half a milligram
or so the goal is to eventually get to
four to 5 milligrams and kind of just
Cruise there indefinitely the biggest
contraindication to taking this is well
concurrent opioid therapy so another
thing to consider is if the patient is
also on immunosuppressants such as U
like Methotrexate or prazone those types
of drugs can possibly reduce the
effectiveness of LDN some considerations
about the actual LDN you get compound
itself well the first one is you should
avoid extended release or sustained
release versions of it again the whole
goal of load out Tre zone is to displace
B you bind displace up regulate bind
displace up regulate is to do that if
you have an extended release formulation
it's almost like having extensive
binding of The receptors and therefore
you're not going to get that
upregulation cycle another thing to
consider it is I've spoken to several
compound pharmacists about this and they
recommend avoiding
LDN that's compounded with calcium
carbonate as a filler so that's what a
lot of Pharmacists have informed me they
say that calcium carbonate if it's
compounded with calcium carbonate as a
filler then that can interfere with the
absorption it can actually negate a lot
of the absorption um however they did
say that sucrose is a fine filler
lactose if you can tolerate it is a fine
filler as well or cellulose so if you're
wondering what are some other conditions
you can use ldm for well this is a great
resource this one I've using for better
part of a decade it's LDN research
trust.org and it displays a whole list a
whole conglomeration of different
conditions you can use for it the ones I
particularly used for was lime disease
um Hashim Modas is on here obviously
I've use it for um eers danlow however
the hell you pronounce that some other
infectious conditions infectious
diseases you can use in here's a big one
long covid
done that only a couple of times but as
you can see there's there's a lot of
different categories that you can use
LDN and here's a whole list of different
cancers and malignancies you can use to
treat it with but the big the big thing
I see that it tends to get the most um
recognition for is in the realm of the
autoimmune diseases that's where ldm
really does play a big role for a lot of
clients and this this website's a
wonderful resource it talks about where
you can find a provider directory it
lists all the different conditions it
even has a whole list of um research and
lots of studies to to actually validate
why you can use LDN well that was a
brief primer on LDN obviously it wasn't
super in depth I want to keep it a
little more superficial just so that if
you are interested or you think this may
be something that's beneficial to you
you have some resources and you have a
little bit of knowledge to think about
with it lastly I like to tell people
that this is an amazing drug it's been
around around they've been researching
it at at the low dose for almost almost
what 45 almost 50 years now give or take
the big thing I always tell folks is it
takes time it it really does I mean once
you even once you even get to your your
cruising dose you know four four and a
half five milligrams I mean you're going
to be there indefinitely I mean three
six 10 months before you start to get
some appreciable benefit so again it's
long and slow play the long game
and hope you enjoy the video